[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
this is philip winston with software
engineering radio i'm here with rahm
sriharsha
rahm is vice president of engineering
and research and development at pinecone
previously he was vice president of
engineering and head of machine learning
at splunk
and before that he worked at databricks
and yahoo
he is on the project management
committee for apache spark
ram has a phd in physics from the
university of maryland
is there anything else in your
background you'd like to highlight no i
think that covers all of it it's great
to be here and thanks for inviting me
great before we get started i wanted to
list two previous episodes we've done on
machine learning and there are others in
the episode history
the first one is episode 391
jeremy howard on deep learning
and episode 286 katie malone
introduction to machine learning
so in this episode we're going to talk a
lot about vectors in the context of
machine learning what are vectors it's a
great question so people are i think
very familiar with the concept of
vectors you might have heard it in other
contexts i would say this appears a lot
in physics and engineering often you're
familiar with quantities that have a
magnitude and maybe a sign these are
what we call scalars a good example is
temperature right temperatures are
scalar similarly there are objects or
quantities that have both a magnitude
and the direction you can think of
velocity displacement acceleration these
are all good examples of vectors one
good way to visualize a vector would be
if you are in an n-dimensional space and
if you take the origin and some point in
that space the line connecting them has
a direction to that point
and that line you can think of as
physically representing a vector these
are concepts that are very familiar to
you from non-machine learning settings
they mean the same thing in machine
learning okay for physics i've done
simulations maybe or computer graphics
in 2d and 3d so in 3d a velocity vector
would have three
components x y and z
in machine learning we're talking about
higher dimensional vectors yeah most of
the time yes that is correct so the only
big difference is the vectors could be
1024 dimensions even bigger okay even
people who aren't too involved in
machine learning have heard of google's
machine learning platform tensorflow
what is a tensor and does it relate to
vectors
that's a great question so again tensor
is it's a concept that may be familiar
to people who have been in fields like
mechanics or fluid dynamics and things
like that i've heard about these sort of
things a good example is stress on a
body right on an object if you think
about a small
ball or a small kind of cube you can
imagine stretching it and compacting it
in three different directions right
three independent directions but you can
also imagine shearing it kind of
applying a force at an angle to it in a
sense to actually measure stress on a on
a three-dimensional object
you can't just have three numbers
you need nine numbers right basically
three independent directions times three
we call this a rank two tensor so
basically it is a stress energy of a
body is a rank two tensor
and higher dimensional examples exist of
this so basically a tensor is nothing
but a generalization of a vector just
like a vector of the generalization of a
scalar
you can think of a rank zero tensor as a
scalar a rank one tensor as a vector and
an example of rank two tensor is stress
energy and so on okay great so since
we're emphasizing the software
engineering aspect i'd like to just talk
briefly about specific data types so
in regular programming i'm usually
choosing between floats and doubles for
my floating point values and those today
i think are generally 32-bit or 64-bit
i've heard in machine learning they
sometimes use 16-bit or even 8-bit
floating point numbers why does machine
learning want lower precision values and
how would i choose what precision to use
we generally tend to use floats a lot in
machine learning but as we mentioned
eight bit 16 bits are also quite common
the two biggest reasons to use this are
for compactness these 8-bit and 16-bit
representations produce just more
compact models the other reason is
sometimes they're actually more amenable
to taking better advantage of the cpu
right so they can actually lead to
faster inference and so on the main
trade-off here is between compactness
and speed versus accuracy so you're
losing a little bit of floating point
position
using 8 bits and 16 bits and so on so
then it's a question of are you accurate
enough
for the speed and for the compactness
and the storage reduced storage
requirements that you gain okay great
that gives us a little idea about
vectors now let's talk about vector
embedding
what does vector embedding mean in the
context of machine learning an embedding
is nothing but a transformation or a
mapping from one vector space to the
other
so a good example could be if you just
take an image and look at the pixels of
the image
the pixels of the image could be say
28 by 28 dimensional right so it could
be a grayscale image of 28 by 28
dimensions and i'm thinking of something
like mnist
that gives you a 784 dimensional kind of
representation of an image now this may
not be the best representation of the
image right this is just capturing the
pixelated version of the image what you
may want to do is to pass it through
some kind of a machine learning model
that learns a lower dimensional
representation that may be better suited
for judging semantic similarity between
images and embedding is nothing but that
basically an embedding is a mapping that
takes some raw representation of your
unstructured data like images or text
and so on and produces a smaller more
compact representation that is a better
fit for your downstream tasks
okay great i just wanted to flag one
acronym or abbreviation you said mnist
what is that mnist is a very popular
image data set so it's a data set of
grayscale images of handwritten digits
and it's very popular as a benchmark
data set okay and i'm not sure if this
follows directly from discussing
embedding but what is feature
engineering and
do the values in my
vector correspond to features or is it
not that simple
yes feature engineering is basically
again any process that takes a raw
representation of your data
and produces a more compact
representation that's better suited for
say classification regression or any of
your downstream tasks
and yes you're right that you can
imagine taking the specific weights of
your vector or the components of your
vector and treating them as features
today a lot of feature engineering comes
from deep learning models and so on
where there is not a direct tie in
between the
coordinate of a vector or like the
actual value of a coordinate to any
semantically meaningful feature but yes
you're right
yeah i was going to ask about deep
learning next when i've looked at
a table of contexts for a course on
machine learning i was surprised there's
quite a few techniques before they even
introduce neural nets let alone deep
learning but
certainly it seems very popular today
how has the rise of deep learning
affected
the type of vector embeddings you see or
how they're created like what has been
the impact of deep learning yeah so
feature engineering has existed for a
long long time before deep learning
mostly people have been doing
handcrafted features they are pretty
time consuming to develop and they
require a lot of domain expertise and in
areas like nlp for example feature
engineering used to mean tf idf sort of
transformations and so on which
basically generates parts vectors
what deep learning i think has done
which is pretty remarkable
is it has made it extremely easy for
anyone to
take a pre-trained model and generate
good enough embeddings so
you can take these models that have been
trained for other tasks
and use them to generate features
that are useful for training for your
task the commercial viability of this
and the availability of high quality
pre-trained models has completely
unlocked and kind of changed this game
so
that is actually why you're seeing a lot
of feature engineering being done by
deep learning models today because of
the availability of the technology and
the ability of these models to produce
very high quality embeddings
that can transfer to your own tasks
yeah i was going to ask about this term
pre-trained later on but let's talk
about it a little now so the idea is
a third party or an expert has done
neural net training done deep learning
training and you use the network they
created but then maybe you add on your
own
special spin on that and that that's
made it easier to people get started in
yes yes that is 100 correct often these
are big companies like google facebook
open ai and so on who have created these
very large free trained models that have
been trained on huge corpuses
and they cost a lot of money quite
frankly to train but these models are
actually once trained they are available
for everyone
even though these models have been
trained on these large public data sets
they capture semantically interesting
representations
that can be useful for your own tasks so
your task may not be anything to do with
wikipedia data sets but
these models are so good that you can
actually use them as a starting point to
fine-tune for your own task and again
that has kind of been a game changer
yeah that's great it sounds like sort of
an evolution of open source in terms of
these are open models i guess that
you're able to use yes
so going back to
vector embedding in the details
you mentioned long vectors i think 10 24
elements what determines the length is
that something that i determine as if
i'm creating the model or is that does
the training actually tell me how long
the vector needs to be that's a great
question so it is what is called a hyper
parameter so it is one of the parameters
that's an input to your process itself
for creating these models as opposed to
it being a learn parameter this is
basically roughly translates to the
number of layers that you you may want
to use in your model again every task is
different so you may want to have
different dimensional embeddings for
different tasks
but often what happens is people take
one of these pre-trained models
and they may use them as a starting
point in which case you you get the
dimensionality of that model or that
embedding as a starting point and which
is usually like 784 1024 dimensions as
well okay you mentioned sparse versus
dense i think it was for for vector
embedding what properties in general
does a good vector embedding have and
how am i able to judge that if i'm
trying to come up with one a good vector
representation has to be both compact as
well as it has to capture the semantic
similarity so basically the main reason
to create these vector embeddings is
that
nearness in the embedding space tells
you something about nearness in your
images or or in the things that you care
about so they have to have semantically
rich content
but they also have to be compact right
so that you can store them easily you
can analyze them easily and you can
query them effectively
that makes sense so we've talked about
vectors and vector embedding before we
go into vector search and vector
databases i wanted to step way back and
give some applications that people might
be familiar with that are probably using
vector search or vector databases under
the hood just something very concrete
that we can think about perhaps a
classic example would be netflix's
recommendation sort of algorithms or in
general any sort of retail product
recommendation the general idea being
that if you have users and you know the
user preference vectors and if you have
say movie ratings and you know the movie
rating vectors
then essentially semantic similarity can
be used or vector search can be used to
tell you for any new user what sort of
movies to recommend essentially by
looking at similarity between user and
movies this sort of idea extends to any
sort of product retail recommendation on
the other end of the spectrum you can
also do things like detecting near
duplicates and images right so if you
have an image and if you have a corpus
of images you may want to find out is
this image a near duplicate of something
that's already in your corpus now it is
easy to find duplicates exact duplicates
but images can be near duplicates in
many ways right they can be slightly
grayed out they can have a small
rotation in the image and things like
that it's extremely hard for you to
physically quantify what makes an image
near duplicate but if you pass this
image through a
embedding model then you can look at the
nearness between the two embeddings and
that can be used to tell you whether the
two images are near duplicates so these
are a couple of examples okay great that
makes a lot of sense it sounds like this
is the type of thing we see all the time
online
these days with services and websites so
yeah let's move into vector search so we
have our vector embedding we've created
vectors i guess for millions of items or
many many items
are we always searching for similarity
or what are we searching for exactly
there is both similarity as well as
anomalies or dissimilarities for example
you can look at similar items you can
also look at what is not similar to
anything that's in your corpus and
that's usually what we call anomaly you
can also use this for classification
sort of tasks which is
you not only retrieve things that are
similar to each other but you can also
look at what you've labeled the things
that have been similar to each other as
and then use the majority label to
predict something this can be used for
classification regression can be used
for similarity it can be used for
anomaly detection
interestingly enough the set of use
cases that vector search powers
is growing by the day and whatever you
would have traditionally thought of as
kind of search can be thought of as a
strict subset of what vectors which can
do so you mentioned classification is
clustering the same thing i saw that
reference on your website i think yeah
yeah clustering is like an unsupervised
technique classification means you have
labels labeled it for you and you want
to given a new point detect whether it
has a certain label
in clustering you're just looking at
things that are close to each other it's
an unsupervised technique and it's very
common either as a pre-processing
technique or
just to identify patterns in your data
okay that's interesting so there are
many types of databases sql key value
store graph databases document databases
how is vector search similar to some of
these existing database types and how is
it different yeah database in the
category of save time series databases
or spatial databases and so on where
you have all the traditional problems of
a database including data management
including freshness including
transactional updates and all the things
that you care about the database
providing you're dealing with a new type
of data right in the case of time series
data it's a new type of data
traditional relational databases aren't
optimized for dealing with time series
data similarly geospatial traditional
databases are not quite optimized for
dealing with geospatial data what makes
vector search even more interesting i
think from from my perspective it's not
just a new type of data or a new
representation of data
it is that vector search
is fundamentally computationally
intensive in a way that not even
geospatial or time series or any of the
other databases have to deal with
it's just
orders of magnitude more computationally
intensive
especially because you're dealing with
this high dimensionality problem and the
sort of algorithms that are to do
indexing of decomposition intensive
it stretches the boundary of what
databases can do so it's not easy for
you to take an existing database and
kind of provide this capability on top
of it but other than that there's a lot
of commonality between
traditional databases and what we are
trying to do here
okay in a typical database we construct
one or more indices to make searching
tractable where index is an additional
data structure that's constructed from
the
input data and it's created and
maintained by the database internally
does vector search require an index and
is it a different type of index yes
vector search requires a specialized
index it's called a k nearest neighbor
search index is the terminology we use
in that sense it is very similar to the
sort of b3 indexes or other indices that
you would have seen in databases the
place where it is different is that
this is basically still cutting edge
research where it is a challenging
problem to come up with indexing
techniques for nearest neighbor search
that are up to date with your data right
they're as up-to-date as your data is
while at the same time being extremely
efficient to query so that is really the
challenge that we trying to solve but
other than that you can morally or
logically think of it between indices or
any other index for a database
okay and just to guide us here what
range of scales do you see developers
creating vector search for what is
typical or what would be on the high end
of scale for uh either the vectors
you're searching over or the number of
queries or any any dimension yeah
there's a few dimensions here one is we
see people creating millions of vectors
we also see people creating billions of
vectors billions of vectors being
searched over so in terms of just volume
there is a pretty big variance in what
we see there is also other challenges
here for example we see people who have
to update their vectors quite often
these are use cases where vectors may
change very often we also see people who
maybe only create a million vectors but
they have to query it with like 100
query queries per second a thousand
pages per second and so on and we also
see people who are perfectly fine with
100 milliseconds or 500 milliseconds or
even a one second latencies during
queries but they just want to be able to
store and query 15 billion or 50 billion
vectors so
the set of use cases we see is quite
varied across multiple dimensions
whether it is freshness of your index
whether it is query throughput or
whether it is ingestion throughput so
and we have to optimize across these
dimensions
so just thinking about the
implementation of that are you
detecting or inferring like what the
usage pattern is and then steering that
to a different implementation or do you
try to have an implementation that can
kind of roll with whatever is being sent
to you
so at a high level we kind of tend to
separate hybrid indexes from in-memory
indexes so basically we have two types
of indexes one that is optimized for
storing as much as possible whereas the
other one is optimized for low latency
queries but that said when we
build indexing algorithms we tend to
build ones that are first of all highly
accurate and have provable accuracy
guarantees but at the same time they're
actually optimized for freshness so
because a lot of our customers actually
prefer freshness we want to build things
that are quick to update and quick to
kind of react to changing data so yes at
a high level we kind of tend to have in
memory index indices that are more
optimized towards query latency
whereas hybrid indexes that are
optimized towards storing massive
amounts of data
but we are very careful in designing
parts of our system so that they can be
reused across these two as much as
possible
yeah that makes sense
so you mentioned k nearest neighbor
search can you explain a little bit more
about how that works and is the k
the number of dimensions in the vector
or is it something else k nearest
neighbor search is one of the earliest
machine learning algorithms and the
algorithm works like this which is it
basically memorizes the training data
set so basically suppose you give it a
training data set it simply stores it
and memorizes it so at a time when you
give it a query it looks for the k
nearest points to that query vector
and it uses the majority label of that
query vector to say that is the label of
this query point the k there comes from
the number of near vectors that it looks
at so k equals 1 means it'll look at the
nearest neighbor and that's it k equals
3 means it looks at three nearest
neighbors and so on so that k doesn't
have anything to do with the
dimensionality of the vector space
itself but more how many near neighbors
we query okay that makes sense yeah
that's good to
disambiguate that
when thinking of the distance between
two vectors the most natural distance
function is probably euclidean which is
the straight line distance between two
points but in machine learning there are
a number of different distance functions
or metrics
can you explain what some of these are
and why or how you would know to use one
of these alternate functions yeah
different
distance measures are useful for
different sort of tasks a good example
is like manhattan distance i think the
name comes actually from the way
the street system or the grid system is
laid out in manhattan right everything
is right angles there so if you wanted
to travel from one point to the other
you're actually following one of the not
south or east west grids
so the distance between two points in a
manhattan grid is no longer the
euclidean distance or the crow flying
distance it is really the distance that
you travel along the north-south edge
and the east-west
so in that case it makes sense to use
manaten distance which is basically the
sum of the distances along the axis
similarly we tend to see cosine distance
being used quite often especially around
text similarity matrix measures and the
main difference there is that cosine
descents cares about the angle between
two vectors it doesn't care about
whether one vector is really large or
really small whereas euclidean distance
it would matter whether the vectors are
small or large right that would
dramatically change the distance between
the two vectors
even if you double this length of a
vector as long as the angle doesn't
change with the other vector the cosine
still doesn't change so depending on the
properties of what you care about in
terms of similarity you may tend to
choose cosine distance in some places
versus completely
so can you give an example of maybe
where one of these distance functions
was inappropriate or would be
inappropriate versus one which would be
sort of a more natural fit yeah tech
similarity is a good example so one of
the reasons why people use cosine
distance there is imagine you just had
two words these two words were the only
two words in your corpus and you can
think of them as being laid out in two
dimensions one of the words being on one
of the axes the other one being on the
other axis when you have a document you
may have a document that has both of
these words and these words may appear
10 times in one document each
the other document may have the same two
words appear once each
now
in the case of cosine distance the
cosine distance between the two
documents would be one because the fact
that you scaled everything by a factor
of 10 or 100 doesn't change the distance
between the two documents which means
the two documents are kind of going to
be very closely related related to each
other in the case of euclidean distance
that may not be true right because the
distance now is much larger simply
because one of the documents had 100
occurrences of each of these words
so that's an example where you don't
want to use a plain distance because you
care about just the fact that the two
words co-occurred
the fact that they co-occurred twice or
thrice doesn't
change that
okay so i can see how it sort of bubbles
up to the
semantics or the meaning of of what
you're actually implementing one more
distance function i saw i'm just curious
if you know offhand where this would be
used was the chebyshev
yes we rarely see it to be honest it's
so i think it's also called the l
infinity distance or something so
basically chebyshev distance if you look
at a distance in two dimensions
euclidean distance would be looking at
the shortest distance between the two
points chebyshev distance looks at the
longest distance you have to travel
along an axis to get to that point i
think this comes across more in in areas
where for example imagine that you had a
crane and you had to take some package
from one point to another in two
dimensions but your crane could only
move in two dimensions right it can only
move but not south or east west
and it moves at the same speed in both
directions
which means if you want to measure how
how long it takes to get from one point
to the other
you will use the chebyshev distance
because
all it matters is what is the maximum
distance in a particular access you have
to travel because in that same time
you're going to be traveling the other
axis anyway
so it's an example of that so it's
probably in like warehouse logistics and
things like that you would end up using
something like this but
honestly we don't see that too often
that particular metric i haven't
encountered too often
okay that's interesting i can imagine
some distant metrics are more popular or
more common than other ones so you
mentioned vector search is
computationally intensive are these
distance functions part of that
difficulty is that a consideration are
there more expensive or cheaper distance
functions or is that not really where
the cost is coming from
there is a lot of the cost that we have
to pay before we even have to worry
about distance functions the biggest
challenge with nearest neighbor search
is exact nearest neighbor search is just
computationally infeasible right so
exact nearest neighbor search or the
simple algorithm would simply be
if i give you a query point scan the
entire database
you know exactly the difference between
each of the query points to every other
point in your database and just sort it
and figure out what the top k are that's
like the naive algorithm that simply
doesn't scale it doesn't scale because
the corpus is huge it also doesn't scale
because the number of dimensions is very
high
the other challenge that happens
even if you say don't want the exact
search and you're okay with
approximation approximation itself has
challenges in high dimensions so there's
something called curves of
dimensionality
because of which
once you go into higher dimensions even
even designing approximate nearest
neighbor algorithms becomes very
challenging right and any sort of exact
algorithm kind of isn't any better than
the naive album
so these are the bigger challenges we
have to solve
but when designing such algorithms
sometimes some of them may not have good
approximation guarantees for
a generic metric for example they may
only have really good approximation
guarantees for cosine distance right
these are things we have to worry about
but usually the problems are even even
earlier than that yeah i was going to
bring up approximate nearest neighbors
since it sounds like that's what's
actually used with any appreciable
scale what determines just how
approximate the results are is that a
question of how
long you spend evaluating the results or
is it a question of the algorithm if i
have a knob between
very approximate and less approximate
how would that work
when people use the word approximate
it's a little bit hand-wavy meaning
there are algorithms out there that are
called approximate nearest thing by
search algorithms but the extent of
approximation is unknown a good example
is things like h and sw these are really
great algorithms by the way but there
are no guaranteed bounds on
approximation so it's not like you can
tune a knob and the more you can tune
that now the better the approximation
gets it's not like that that is not the
case for algorithms that we develop at
pinecone in fact the algorithms we
develop have like a tunable now so you
can actually if you wanted tune a knob
to get higher accuracy if you wanted
the other thing we do and also when
machine learning scientists talk about
approximate nearest neighbor search they
usually mean something very precise
which is
they mean that
this algorithm is going to give you a
point
that is within
one plus epsilon or a small small fudge
factor
away from
a point within the distance you care
about you can make this very precise and
those are the sort of algorithms that we
developed so when machine learning
literature talks about approximate
nearest neighbor algorithms they are
they have a very strong guarantee which
is there is a trade-off between how
close to correct or exact you are versus
how much memory and space and time
that algorithm takes but in practice a
lot of algorithms you see out there
don't have this property very few of
them do
so the vector search portion of let's
say our machine learning application
is not necessarily or or maybe it's not
evaluating a neural network at that
point
is that true or is it possible to have a
distance function that itself is
learned or itself is a neural network
by the time we get vectors in a sense
the training has already been done so
the model has been trained and people
are sending the
unstructured data through the models to
get an embedding and we store those
embeddings and query them
as part of training you can also do
what's called metric learning which is
to actually learn the distance function
itself people can do that now there is
no way they can do that on top of
pinecone today because for us we get the
embeddings but it's certainly something
that people can do there is a lot of
literature on how to do this
that's certainly a trend we see in
software engineering is that something
that was complex and manual is becoming
learned by deep learning or similar
technique
so we've talked about vector search
we've kind of veered into vector
databases also but now i want to focus
on
vector databases and pine cones so can
you explain what was the motivation in
creating the service what did you see
in the industry
that this service was trying to meet
big companies like netflix google and so
on have been developing this sort of
technology over the last few years a lot
of what we do is bringing
what has only been available to a few
big companies so far into the mass
market and making it a sas product that
anyone can use so
i would say that's what we focus on
today we now know how to do this and now
it's just a matter of scaling it and
making it available to everyone
at the same time embeddings have become
very popular and it's become very easy
for people to
get millions and billions of embeddings
and kind of work with them which has
unlocked a lot of new use cases for them
the main challenge for many of these
customers is cost and scale
so
if you don't make things 100x less
costly it simply doesn't unlock certain
use cases right so big companies can
afford to spend millions and millions of
dollars on some of these technologies
but most companies cannot what we are
trying to do is to bring the cost down
to a point where
people can benefit from these emerging
use cases that they wouldn't otherwise
and since nothing existed that could do
this we started the company
around that can i ask what pinecone
stands for or where the name pine cone
came from i think they had to change the
name because there was like some clash
between the original name that we had
picked
and we've kind of brainstormed
apparently for names and pinecone was
the name that stood out
but as far as i can tell there's no cool
reason
for choosing paint cone okay we talked a
little bit about maybe the interface
between what pinecone does and what the
developer or customer is doing can you
talk a little bit more about that what
am i sending to you is the customer
hitting your api or how is that the end
user hitting your api how does that work
we provide multiple types of apis http
python and so on so all you do is you
use our apis you can spin up as many
indices as you want
you can size them however you want and
you get these apis through which you can
submit vectors metadata to us
you can do data management you can also
do queries again some of these will
evolve over time but today our focus we
are kind of razor focused on building
the world's best vector database which
means our focus is on people who already
have embeddings
once you have those embeddings you kind
of send them to us
you can use pinecone to query it over
time
we may also kind of start helping people
who don't have embeddings but who have a
lot of unstructured data but today we
expect people to have embeddings yeah
that makes sense so you kind of alluded
to this but what are some more
operational challenges with running
vector search at scale what problems did
you have to solve that maybe every
developer does not want to deal with
all the common problems of elastically
scaling such a service exists so for
example since embeddings essentially are
coming from unstructured data and
unstructured data is growing
exponentially for customers
right off the bat we have to build
something that has to directly
elastically scale right because people
are just throwing more and more data
over time
so those cloud elasticity problems
already exist for us
but on top of that what's really
challenging is in building the
technology that makes efficient indexing
possible
so a lot of the time we spend is on how
do you ingest
data
like large volumes of data fast and how
do you adapt your indices so that they
can kind of get up to date fast
at the same time how do you take
advantage of modern hardware whether it
is ssds whether it is specialized cpu
instructions available on these cloud
machines and so on
to drive down the cost for queries and
costs for storing all this data
so most of our time is spent in
optimizing for cost scale
and freshness and these are all hard
problems just because of the nature of
that research being a computationally
intensive problem
right one aspect of scaling that doesn't
get talked about much is scaling down i
know you give out api keys for people to
try the service i imagine a lot of
developers have uploaded test data and
maybe they only do a few
test queries were there any
engineering decisions that were specific
to hosting this long tail of smaller
databases
yes so
we have a multi-tenant kind of service
that people use if you have a very small
database in fact a free tier if you have
one million vectors and so on you can
just spin up a very tiny part with a
small part you can kind of do a lot of
queries one of the things we are doing
also is things like offloading data to
block storage so
you can spin down your instances and you
won't lose data we are very mindful of
those sort of use cases which may be
smaller and you may not be querying it
all the time but when you need to query
it you need to quickly bring up an index
and kind of
do your work
so you kind of mentioned this but i'm
interested for a typical machine
learning
application how often the model gets
updated i think you kind of discussed
this but
can you give an example of an
application where you might perform
millions of searches with the same model
the model is calculated just once or an
application when the model needs to be
updated frequently and how does pinecone
support both of these extremes yeah
there are actually quite a few use cases
where you train a model once and you
kind of create embeddings and those
embeddings are very stable often when
you think about documents and searching
documents and so on
if these documents don't change quite
often you can treat these embeddings as
being generated once and then you're
more often searching than updating the
vectors
on the other hand if you look at use
cases like advertising product
recommendations and things like that
user preferences change quite rapidly
right so especially in advertising what
a user did five minutes back or even a
few minutes back
impacts their decision
now much more than what they did
days or weeks passed
so because of that user preferences tend
to change quite rapidly
and models that use user preferences to
do semantic search or any sort of
product recommendation
style search
need to deal with updated embeddings in
a much shorter time scale and we are
talking about time scales of less than a
minute so we see both of these use cases
so kind of more common use case for
updating vectors
quite rapidly
is advertising retail recommendation
product recommendations and so on
less common is in the text search or
image search areas
yeah i can see that i saw a lot of
examples on your site with natural
language processing and a few with
images
how do the requirements differ in these
two domains or in other domains that you
could classify
that you see
some differences could be as simple as
dimensionality right so we tend to see
higher dimensional embeddings for images
for example we do tend to see up to 20
48 dimensions
now higher dimensions obviously is means
it's computationally more challenging in
text we usually see lower dimensions
even up to 128 dimensions and so on we
do see that other than that
there aren't a whole again the size of
the corpus may be very different so
image search sometimes we don't see that
many images in text search you could see
if you think about transcripts of sales
calls or transcripts of conversations
and so on they can get extremely big you
do tend to see some diversity in terms
of just the number of vectors the
dimensionality of the vectors and so on
okay let's start wrapping up related to
to what you're just discussing what are
the most challenging parts of a
developer interested in setting up a
vector search application what do you
consider is is still hard today
i think we are working on a lot of the
hard parts i would say that with
pinecone i would say i'm very
comfortable and happy with saying that
we made it easy for developers to get
started
we made it extremely easy for you to
spin up a pinecone instance
ingest your data analyze it and query it
and people are able to build successful
applications with
near zero effort and we strive for that
at the beginning we wanted to make it as
simple as possible humanly possible
wherever you're spending a lot of effort
is like i said in making this as cost
effective as possible i feel like there
is still a lot we can do here to make
this technology far more cost effective
than it is today
and also scale it far more than you can
do today like for example we are focused
very heavily but i am very happy with
what we've done so far in terms of being
able to reduce the barrier to entry of
this sort of technology to a developer
so developers are able to today ingest
data and get productive and be able to
build applications extremely quickly and
these
continue to double down on that
okay you're operating a specific niche
within the larger machine learning
universe where do you see things
involving in general that's going to
impact you or machine learning
techniques or just any trends that you
see on the horizon that you're watching
the biggest trend i think which we we
also want to take advantage of is while
we are working on a very specific niche
which is a vector database there is this
overall trend
that data is becoming more and more
unstructured unstructured data is
exploding compared to what traditionally
used to be relational data so more and
more of what people are going to be
doing with unstructured data
is going to be using machine learning
and it's going to be using technologies
like what we're building
how do we take what we built today and
close the gap with unstructured data
which is today we need people to have
embeddings today we need people to have
certain amount of sophistication with
machine learning to be able to use
pinecone and so on
but
there is vastly more unstructured data
than there are embeddings and how do you
get people who have a lot of such data
and they have really interesting
business use cases but they don't have
teams of data centers and a lot of
expertise in machine learning how do you
help them this is something that we'll
have to solve because
the amount of data we are talking about
is
exploring and the use cases are
exploring
okay i think that's a great place to end
can you tell the listeners where to find
out more information about pinecone and
then also about you specifically and i
can put both into the show notes for
people to look up our website
pinecone.io has a lot of information we
also have a lot of example notebooks and
we have a free tier so anyone can sign
up and kind of play around with pinecone
and give us feedback we'd love to hear
from you if anything here resonated with
any of you please feel free to reach out
i'll say that i did look at the learn
section of your website and i was pretty
impressed with the depth of some of the
articles and
i found it very interesting thanks for
your time today rahm this is philip
winston for software engineering radio
thank you
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening